<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[CUBE PUSHER]]></title>
  <link href="http://cubepusher.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cubepusher.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-05T17:47:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://cubepusher.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Stephen Tudor]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Innovation]]></title>
    <link href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/innovation/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-06T20:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cubepusher.com/blog/innovation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/63888/innovation">Innovation</a>
(2010) is a card game by Carl Chudyk, published by Asmadi Games (not to be
confused with Asmodee).</p>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/JxK5/innovation_300.jpeg" alt="Innovation" /></p>

<p>You might recognize the name of the designer if you are familiar with <em>Glory to
Rome</em>, the game for which Chudyk may be best known. Like GtR, <em>Innovation</em> is
a card game with some very interesting and original mechanics. It is themed
around civilization, which is pretty much a guaranteed buy for me. I have no
self-restraint when it comes to civ-themed games; I want to try ‘em all!</p>

<p>In practice, <em>Innovation</em> turns out to be more of an interactive tech tree
than a typical civilization game. However, to quote Kip Dynamite, “I
love technology…”</p>

<h2>The Components</h2>

<p>Each of the 110 cards in <em>Innovation</em> is unique. Cards represent
technological advancements that characterized human history as we know
it. The game begins with techs like <strong>The Wheel</strong> and <strong>Agriculture</strong>,
and in the most modern era, includes techs like <strong>Databases</strong> and <strong>The
Internet</strong>. The cards are separated into piles, one for each “Age” of
history (Ancient all the way up through the Digital Age). What’s more, 1
card from each Age is selected face-down and set aside as an Achievement
to be earned with points, forming a sort of “kitty” in the middle of the
table so the overall pool of cards in play cannot be known at the
outset. There are also 5 “special” Achievement cards that can be earned
by satisfying specific conditions, like having so many of a particular
symbol, or having all top cards of a certain level in play.</p>

<p>That’s it. Just a big deck of cards, some player mats, and a lot of
’splaining to do…</p>

<p><a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/image/932325/innovation"><img src="http://2dr.se/JwXo/pic932325_md.jpeg" title="Cards" alt="Cards" /></a></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/msaari">Mikko Saari</a></em></p>

<h2>The Goal</h2>

<p>Players’ general objective in <em>Innovation</em> is to obtain Achievements by
various means. Picking up a certain number of Achievements is the
primary victory condition of the game. Certain cards in later Ages have
alternate winning conditions as well. The game also has a built-in
“clock” as a winning condition, in that, if a player attempts to draw a
card from Age 10 (the highest pile) and there are no cards left, the
player with the highest score (not Achievements) wins. The alternate
winning conditions add a tension to the game that I rather enjoy…
multiple paths to victory and all that.</p>

<h2>The Gameplay</h2>

<p>In play, cards come in 5 different colors, and each contains text
describing particular effects listed on it along with an associated
symbol, as well as 3 large symbols that add to the strength of a
player’s tableau in those areas. These symbols, and the strategy behind
stacking, are what makes the card actions so interesting. When a player
plays a card of the same color as a card already in your play area, the
first card must be covered by the newly played card, creating a stack,
and thus concealing the pre-existing card. This is important, because in
Innovation, when it comes to symbol counts and executing card actions,
only the top-most cards count. However, there are ways to “splay”
(spread) stacks of cards in various directions, which exposes 1-3
symbols on cards in the stack underneath the top card.</p>

<p>On a player’s turn, he can take two actions, in any order: <strong>draw</strong> a
card from an Age pile into his hand, <strong>meld</strong> (play) a card from his
hand to his board, <strong>achieve</strong> (take an achievement if the requirements
are met), or take a <strong>dogma</strong> action allowed by a top card in his board.
A player can achieve twice, achieve and draw, draw twice, draw and meld,
etc.</p>

<p>That’s as far as I will go with covering rules specifics. Let me just say that
while the rules are extremely straightforward, the cards are less so. However,
in contrast to a game like <em>Race for the Galaxy</em> (one of my all-time
favorites), there is no encyclopedia worth of iconography to learn – every card
does exactly what it says, and the game uses a vocabulary that is very easy to
get familiar with.</p>

<h2>The Reckoning</h2>

<p>At the core of <em>Innovation</em> is the variety of special powers made
available to a player by each card’s dogma actions. Dogma actions can
break the rules in some pretty crazy ways, and yes, the potential for
constructing card combos is pretty huge. For example, using the Paper
technology with the <strong>Perspective</strong> technology is a combination that can
create a formidable scoring engine. Believe me, there are far more, and
many that I haven’t discovered yet.</p>

<p><em>Innovation</em> is an almost purely tactical game. As it is a card game, luck
of the draw is a major component, and there isn’t much getting around
the very real possibility of a player top-decking his way to victory.
The nature of the cards make wild swings of fate fairly prevalent, which
is a double-edged sword: on one hand, a player can slap down a killer
combo that lifts his civilization up out of the ashes, or even win the
game outright. On the other hand, a player will sometimes be able to
build up such a head of steam that he ends up being unstoppable, and
rolls effortlessly for the win.</p>

<p>For some, this kind of chaos can be somewhat off-putting. It’s true that
with a full complement of 4 players, <em>Innovation</em> can be very chaotic
indeed.</p>

<p>For fans of other medium- to high-complexity strategy card games such as
<em>Magic: The Gathering</em> or <em>Race for the Galaxy</em>, <em>Innovation</em> should be a big
draw. It is very different from most other games of its kind, which
makes it worthy of adding to most any game collection.</p>

<p>To date, I’ve played <em>Innovation</em> over a dozen times, and each play has
been completely different and interesting in its own way. As you can see
in my <a href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/2010-retrospective">2010 Retrospective</a>, I am a fan of it.
<em>Innovation</em> also won a Golden Geek for
<a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/wiki/page/BoardGameGeek_Golden_Geek">Best Card Game</a>
in 2010.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2010 Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/2010-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2011-01-06T22:01:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://cubepusher.com/blog/2010-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I haven’t exactly been a prolific gamer over the past few years, even at
my peak. This year, though, my board game plays plummeted, and there’s a
good reason for that. Three, actually. That’s the number of people in my
family now, and 2010 was my wife’s and my first full year spent together
with a little one in the house. It’s been quite an experience, to say
the least!</p>

<p>I still found time to play plenty of games, though, and the overall
numbers for the year were bolstered by trips to the WBC and to
EuroQuest, the latter of which was a birthday present from my family.
I’m grateful to them for helping to make that happen, and I really
enjoyed myself. While there, I had the opportunity to play some of the
fresh Essen titles months before they actually made it to the US, which
was a huge treat. Another boost to games played came from an
unlooked-for source: work. Occasionally, some of my co-workers and I
would sit down to a lunchtime game at the office. These were typically
short “filler” games, but that’s the perfect fit for lunchtime at work.</p>

<p>There is a lot to my gaming history that I won’t share here, but
shortly, it will become clear to most other gamers how much of a
lightweight I am in this world of boards, cards, and little wooden
cubes. Still, I have some experiences worth sharing, and perhaps some of
them will be useful to seasoned and aspiring gamers alike. I’ve
certainly played my share of games… it’s just when I look at how many
plays some other game bloggers have, I look like a halfhearted dabbler
by comparison (and, admittedly, a pretty envious dabbler at that).</p>

<p>I’ll start with an overview of my paltry stats first, then move to the
“special awards”, and finally close out with my personal Top 5 of the
year.</p>

<h1>2010 Stats</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jwy3/games-played-graph.png" title="Games Played by Year" alt="Games Played by Year" /></p>

<p>I played 68 distinct games in 2010, and I had 104 total plays all year.
This is down about 15% from 2009, and down about 35% from my 2008
counts. Still, it’s much higher than I would have thought before
actually looking at the numbers, so I’m thankful.</p>

<p>There are only 2 nickels (games that I played 5 or more times) on the
list: <em>Innovation</em> and San Juan. I’m not a huge San Juan fan, but the guys
at work like to play it, and I’m not about to argue when there’s a
chance to squeeze a play in over lunch break. Innovation is up there
because my non-gamer wife has taken a liking to it, and has beat me more
than once (further boosting its spouse appeal)!</p>

<p>Of the 68 games I got to play, 55% of those were new games, about the
same ratio as the two previous years. It’s nice to know I’m consistent
in one area: I do like to try new games quite a bit. Of my total plays
in 2010, 47 were single plays, about 69%. That’s pretty close to the
past couple of years as well.</p>

<p>I’ve done a rather bad job of keeping track of my game acquisition
stats, but I’ll hopefully get that in order for next year’s reckoning.
Suffice it to say that I own far too many games for how often I get to
play them. However, I am working on raising a future gamer. Only 5 more
years (or so) till he’s ready for Puerto Rico. ;)</p>

<p>In summary, not great numbers by any stretch, but I played games when I
could and enjoyed other aspects of life the rest of the time. Maybe 2011
will be kinder to this gamer (it’s not looking that way!).</p>

<h1>Special Award: Biggest Surprise</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jxt1/dom-spec.jpeg" title="Dominant Species" alt="Dominant Species" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/Raid1280">Raid1280</a></em></p>

<p>The game that totally came out of nowhere this year was <em>Dominant
Species</em>. There was minimal news and buzz surrounding its release, but
people started absolutely raving about it once it got published. I was
certainly impressed with it after just reading the rules, but my one
play of Dominant Species confirmed that it’s the real deal. It’s
surprising too how “nasty, brutish, and short” the life of a species can
be.</p>

<h3>Runners-up: Thunderstone, Peloponnes</h3>

<h1>Special Award: Biggest Disappointment</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/JxOX/twi-imp.jpeg" title="Twilight Imperium" alt="Twilight Imperium" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/Konwacht">Kon Wacht</a></em></p>

<p>I don’t like to say negative things about games, so I’ll keep this
short. I sat through a nightmarishly long <em>Twilight Imperium, Third
Edition</em> for 9 hours (!!!) on Black Friday. I could have played 4-5
other games during this period that were actually fun. It gave me a
splitting headache and made me want to punch kittens. I was very excited
to play TI3, and was severely let down.</p>

<h3>Dishonorable Mention: Campaign Manager 2008, Age of Industry</h3>

<h1>Special Award: Best “New to me” Game</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/JxCV/twi-str.jpeg" title="Twilight Struggle" alt="Twilight Struggle" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/halobungieman">halobungieman</a></em></p>

<p><em>Twilight Struggle</em> is a mainstay atop the <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/browse/boardgame">BGG
ranking</a> for some reason.
I decided to find out what that reason was this year, and it turned out
to be pretty rewarding. I played it 3 times throughout the course of the
year, not bad at all for a longer game. It’s a great game that every
gamer should try at least once. I know I haven’t even scratched the
surface of this one. The rules are so simple, but the decisions are so
tough, and the game has a wide-open feel that should let creative
thinkers run wild.</p>

<h3>Runners-up: Innovation, London</h3>

<h1>Special Award: Best Filler</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jwg0/rol-thr.jpeg" title="Roll Through the Ages" alt="Roll Through the Ages" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/Gryphon%20Eagle">Gryphon Eagle</a></em></p>

<p>I define filler as a game that takes roughly 30 minutes or less to play.
<em>Roll Through the Ages</em> fits that requirement and takes the cake. It’s
an incredibly fun and fast-paced dice-rolling game that incorporates a
Yahtzee-like civ-building/scoring mechanic. It’s also over quickly,
perfect for playing in between longer games, or to start or close a
gaming session.</p>

<h3>Runners-up: 7 Wonders, Money</h3>

<h1>Special Award: Best Gateway Game</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/JxSx/tobago.jpeg" title="Tobago" alt="Tobago" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/thdizzy">thdizzy</a></em></p>

<p>I was introduced to <em>Tobago</em> by Kevin (@seizeyourturn) and his wife.
It’s simply charming, complete with awesome components, an accessible
treasure-hunting theme, and a novel deduction mechanic that narrows down
the locations of buried treasure on the island. Did I mention the
awesome components?</p>

<h3>Runners-up: Acquire, Samarkand</h3>

<h1>Special Award: Most Thematic Game</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jx7u/mer-mar.jpeg" title="Merchants &amp; Marauders" alt="Merchants &amp; Marauders" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/Omega%20Wolf">Omega Wolf</a></em></p>

<p>Avast! <em>Merchants &amp; Marauders</em> be th’ game fer ye. Arrr, it’s a pretty
impres­si’e game, with lots t’ think about and a great feel. On the run
from pirates, I verily felt like a mer­chant in th’ Caribbean, ahoy, but
ye can turn pirate and start collectin’ bounties at any time. Me liked
the upgradable ships an’ the sea bat­tles. A pence for an old man o’de
sea?</p>

<h3>Runners-up: Tales of the Arabian Nights, Railways of the World</h3>

<h1>Special Award: Lunch @ Work Game</h1>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jxi8/carc.jpeg" title="Carcassonne" alt="Carcassonne" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/ZaNaBoZa">ZaNaBoZa</a></em></p>

<p>What plays quickly and has the shortest possible setup time?
<em>Carcassonne</em>, of course. Just set out 2 stacks of tiles, and off you
go. This one has turned out to be ideal for lunchtime gaming at the
office. I’m not very good at Carc, nor do I own a copy, but I’ll almost
never turn down a game of this if I’m at the office and have time (the
latter condition occurs less often these days, sadly).</p>

<h3>Runners-up: San Juan, Mamma Mia</h3>

<h1>Top 5 Games of 2010</h1>

<p>Just a note of clarification. Before I get into these, let me point out
that <strong>none of this really means anything</strong>. My thoughts on these games
are purely subjective, so I encourage you to take it with a grain of
salt, and post your own reviews if your tastes differ from mine.</p>

<h2>5. <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/25292/merchants-marauders">Merchants &amp; Marauders</a></h2>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jx5z/mer-mar2.jpeg" title="Merchants &amp; Marauders" alt="Merchants &amp; Marauders" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/henk.rolleman">Henk Rolleman</a></em></p>

<p>I really want to play this one more, and I really can’t say that about
most games these days. An automatic berth on the 5-spot.</p>

<h2>4. <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/33160/endeavor">Endeavor</a></h2>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jwo1/endeavor.jpeg" title="Endeavor" alt="Endeavor" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/Matic">Matic</a></em></p>

<p>It’s a good sign that I’m still into this one. I heavily anticipated
<em>Endeavor</em>’s release and haven’t been disappointed in it one iota.
<em>Endeavor</em> boasts a tense balance of timing, area control, hand
management, and action optimization, all within an attractive and
accessible package.</p>

<h2>3. <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/28143/race-for-the-galaxy">Race for the Galaxy</a></h2>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/JwiF/race.jpeg" title="Race for the Galaxy" alt="Race for the Galaxy" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/Utumo">Utumo</a></em></p>

<p>I’ve been pretty high on <em>Race</em> this year. Its depth and richness of
strategy is tough to beat, and it’s just a card game! Experienced
players can also play this pretty quickly, a big plus. I probably have
about 100 plays of this under my belt, by far my most-played game. With
the 3 expansions, Race continues to challenge and mystify me.</p>

<h2>2. <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/63888/innovation">Innovation</a></h2>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/Jy4K/innovation.jpeg" title="Innovation" alt="Innovation" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/EndersGame">EndersGame</a></em></p>

<p>A highly impressive game from the designer of <em>Glory to Rome</em>. Its one
problem is in scalability: it has a very zero-sum feel for two players,
but may be too chaotic with four. Three seems to be the sweet spot. Yes,
there is randomness and chaos, but such is the nature of card games, and
it plays so fast that it’s easy to just start over with a new game.</p>

<p>And that leaves us with my favorite game of the year:</p>

<h2>1. <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/73439/troyes">Troyes</a></h2>

<p><img src="http://2dr.se/JxYf/troyes.jpeg" title="Troyes" alt="Troyes" /></p>

<p><em>Photo by <a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/user/lacxox">lacxox</a></em></p>

<p><em>Troyes</em> is a really special game, of a breed I haven’t seen a lot of in
my short gaming career. I’ve been trying to stay away from the 2010
Essen games, but in this case I just can’t resist <em>Troyes</em>. It’s right up
there with El Grande and Caylus as one of the finer examples of modern
game design. I don’t know that <em>Troyes</em> will ever be ranked as highly as
those, but it’s a deceptively deep game with a lot going on, making for
a nice blend of tactics and strategy. The dice mechanic is a stroke of
absolute brilliance.</p>

<h3>Honorable Mentions: Twilight Struggle, Macao, London</h3>

<h1>That’s it!</h1>

<p>Well, that’s all I’ve got. What do you think of my Top 5, and how would
yours be different? What were some other games you enjoyed this past
year? Feel free to hit me up on Twitter or post comments below.</p>

<p>This “Year in Review” article was heavily inspired by
<a href="http://hiewandboardgames.blogspot.com/2010/12/my-2010.html">Hiew Chok Sien</a> and
<a href="http://gamerchris.com/2011/01/06/2010-year-in-review.aspx?ref=rss">Chris Norwood</a>,
whose stalwart gaming blogs are radiant lighthouses to my dim,
flickering flashlight.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dominion]]></title>
    <link href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/dominion/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-11T15:29:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cubepusher.com/blog/dominion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a short time, the card game
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/36218/dominion">Dominion</a> (2008) by
Donald X. Vaccarino has become immediately popular and spurred several
expansions. With its concise rules, it offers quick, addictive play in a
format that is easily teachable. Strangely, it takes the most boring
mechanic of collectible card games (i.e., building your deck) and turns
that into the core mechanic of the game. Yet in refining the rules, it
has made an unique, expandable, and portable game that deserves its
accolades as a “filler” type of game that doesn’t feel shallow at all.</p>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/JxGp/pic411789_lg.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/Jxul/pic411789_lg-300x236.jpg" title="What's in the box" alt="What's in the box" /></a>\</p>

<p><em>photo by Francois Haffner (<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/user/Haffner">BGG</a>)</em></p>

<h3>Components &amp; Setup</h3>

<p><em>Dominion</em> is played entirely with cards: there is no board, tokens,
scoresheet, or player mats. Instead, there are 25 action cards (of 10
each) plus three denominations of money and three types of victory
cards. Setup is wonderfully simple. It takes a few minutes and is as
simple as choosing ten cards out of the 25 action cards in the box and
putting those stacks in the center of the table along with three
standard stacks of money cards and three stacks of victory cards.
Everyone gets the same starting deck of three victory points and seven
money cards. It couldn’t be simpler.</p>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/Jwvk/pic397759_lg.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/Jxxf/pic397759_lg-300x188.jpg" title="Starting hand" alt="Starting hand" /></a>\</p>

<p><em>photo by Ender Wiggins (<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/user/EndersGame">BGG</a>)</em></p>

<h3>Gameplay</h3>

<p>Each player deals five cards off the top of their deck and reveals them
to everyone. From that hand, game play can be summed by a clever ABC
acronym. Gamers have one Action: they can use a action card. They have
one Buy, which means they can use the money in that hand to buy an item
in the center of the table (a victory point, action card, or money).
They must then Clean up, which means to discard their hand into their
discard pile. The next player starts the same process. When you run out
of cards in your deck, shuffle them and repeat.</p>

<p>When any three stacks of cards in the center of the table are gone (or
if the 6 point victory card stack is gone), the game is over. Players
sift their stack and count all of the victory points in it. The player
with the highest total of victory points wins.</p>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/JwU7/pic392195_lg.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/Jxxw/pic392195_lg-300x199.jpg" title="Card stacks" alt="Card stacks" /></a>\</p>

<p><em>photo by Gary James (<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/user/garyjames">BGG</a>)</em></p>

<p>It sounds too simple, but I didn’t mention that the action cards are
incredibly clever and varied. Some cards let you attack other players,
give you extra money, lets you trash dead cards in your own deck, give
you bonuses in the end of the game, or steal cards from other players.
There are also cards that have an additional action on them, so if you
activate them with your action, you then have an additional action to
use (and if that 2nd card has an action, you can chain these action to
have 3, 4, or maybe even 5 actions). Therefore, your one hand can become
a chain reaction setting yourself ahead of everyone else.</p>

<p>The end goal is to refine their deck so it has the most victory points
but so it also has enough money and actions so you can buy items and
change your outcome. It’s a tricky balance, since you need a deck with
higher victory points than everyone else, but a deck clogged with
victory point cards means that your actions are limited each turn.
Therefore, many players try to trash lower cards and upgrade to higher
cards or fill their deck with a variety. Alternate strategies are to buy
action cards that attack other players or give them curses that deduct
from their victory points. But you’ll find yourself refining your deck
constantly during the game to find that right balance in a game that has
a good amount of skill and luck to keep game play sharp and quick.</p>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/JxcO/pic392260_lg.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/JxkS/pic392260_lg-300x218.jpg" title="Example of a mid-game hand" alt="Example of a mid-game hand" /></a>\</p>

<p><em>photo by Filip Miłuński (<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/user/Filippos">BGG</a>)</em></p>

<h3>What’s Good About It?</h3>

<p>There are many things that make this a worthwhile addition to your
collection. For one, it works well as a gateway game. <em>Dominion</em> is a
quicker cousin to other strategy cards games like <em>Race for the Galaxy</em>
and <em>Magic: The Gathering</em>, but <em>Dominion</em>’s appeal and strategies are more
immediate. It’s a wonderful, portable game that feels meatier than most
fillers and is excellent to teach to new players or to put on the table
while you wait for your game group to arrive.</p>

<p><em>Dominion</em> also works well as a couples game. If I ask my wife what game
she dislikes, it is usually a game that has a “take that” element or a
game where combat is necessary. Whether or not she will agree to play
depends on how much of that is in a game. <em>Lost Cities</em> or <em>Agricola</em> are a
yes, but <em>Battleline</em> or <em>Magic: The Gathering</em> are a no. The beauty of
<em>Dominion</em> is that you can tweak the deck so it has more or less
interaction. With 25 different cards at your command (and many more with
expansions) you can make it more combative (e.g., add thieves or witches
that can attack other players) or simply a competitive solitaire game
(e.g., take the attack cards out, and players are just competing for the
highest score).</p>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/JxuN/pic711077_lg.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/JxIG/pic711077_lg-300x200.jpg" title="Action cards" alt="Action cards" /></a>\</p>

<p><em>photo by Mike Hulsebus (<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/user/mikehulsebus">BGG</a>)</em></p>

<h3>Concluding Thoughts</h3>

<p><em>Dominion</em> is quick (20-30 minutes), replayable, portable, configurable,
tactical, and unique. It plays well with any number of players (2-4 out
of the box, but expandable to 8); few games scale so perfectly without
adding downtime. The multiple expansions for <em>Dominion</em> add new flavor to
games and keep it fresh and surprising, but even the base game offers
tons of replayability and variety for hundreds of plays.</p>

<h3>Where Can I Buy Dominion?</h3>

<p><em>Dominion</em> won a <strong>ton</strong> of gaming awards in 2009, including the prestigious
Spiel des Jahres, the Deutcher Spiele Preis, and the BGG Golden Geek.
This is a really big deal, and as a result of the critical exposure,
it’s hard <em>not</em> to find a copy of Dominion even if you are just looking
for it in passing. It’s on Amazon, I’ve seen it on shelves at Target and
Barnes &amp; Noble, and, of course,
<a href="https://www.gamesurplus.com/">all</a>
<a href="http://www.coolstuffinc.com/">the</a>
<a href="http://thoughthammer.com/">major</a>
<a href="http://boardsandbits.com/">online</a>
<a href="http://www.fairplaygames.com/">gaming</a>
<a href="http://www.timewellspent.org/">retailers</a>
<a href="http://funagain.com/">carry</a>
<a href="http://boardgameratings.com/">it</a>.</p>

<p>The success of <em>Dominion</em> has also made possible several expansions, which
are also widely available.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keldon's Race for the Galaxy AI]]></title>
    <link href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/keldon-race-for-the-galaxy-ai/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-15T21:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cubepusher.com/blog/keldon-race-for-the-galaxy-ai</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my personal favorite game bloggers,
<a href="http://hiewandboardgames.blogspot.com/">Hiew</a>, recently wrote up a
couple of
<a href="http://hiewandboardgames.blogspot.com/2010/08/race-for-galaxy-brink-of-war.html">nice</a><a href="http://hiewandboardgames.blogspot.com/2010/07/good-ai-bad-ai.html">pieces</a>
that feature Keldon’s <a href="http://www.keldon.net/rftg/">AI software for Race for the Galaxy</a>.</p>

<p>Playing against the <em>Race</em> AI is a challenging and satisfying endeavor. At
first, I won less than 20% of my 2-player games, but now that I’ve had
some practice, I’m hovering around <del>60</del>40% (the <em>Brink of War</em>
expansion just came out, and I’m getting familiar with the strategy
still). Like Hiew, even though I have well over 100 games under my belt
by this point, I feel like a very mediocre player. What’s more, I still
learn something new about <em>Race</em> every time I play.</p>

<p>That, friends, is <strong>depth</strong>. It’s a testament not only to the quality of
the game itself, but also to that of Keldon’s AI software. I downloaded
the source to have a look under the hood, and though I’m hardly a Tcl
developer, the code appears to be very soundly designed and well
thought-out. Granted, it lacks the polished user interaction of a
commercial app, but for a free download, I’m impressed.</p>

<p>What’s more, Keldon recently updated the app to include the most recent
expansion, <em>Brink of War</em>, and this new version includes networked
multiplayer (read: human vs. human) support. I have not played against
many human players yet, but look forward to doing so.</p>

<p>In the same spirit as Hiew’s posts on the subject, below are a few
screenshots and descriptions of the results of some recent games of RFTG
I’ve played using Keldon’s platform. Obviously, you’ll need to have
played <em>Race</em> a few times to appreciate any of this, but perhaps it will
make some curious enough to check the game out.</p>

<p>All three games were 3-player games, me vs. two AI players, with all
three expansions in play and takeovers active.</p>

<h3>Game 1: Uplift Smackdown</h3>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/JwoU/http://2dr.se/JwoU/uplift_smackdown.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/Jx6l/uplift_smackdown_sm.jpg" title="Uplift Smackdown" alt="Screenshot - Uplift Smackdown" /></a></p>

<p>In the first game, I began with <strong>Doomed World</strong>, which I discarded for a
turn-3 <strong>Armaments World</strong>. I actually laid down a 6-cost development,
<strong>Pan-Galactic Research</strong>, on turn 2, which is very unusual for me, but it
paid off big. I had <strong>Uplift Code</strong> in my hand early, and I started slapping
down Uplift worlds like crazy. I also was able to achieve some kind of
crazy Imperium synergy with both <strong>Imperium Seat</strong> and <strong>Imperium Lords</strong>,
topping off my tableau with the 7-cost <strong>Rebel Homeworld</strong> and the 9-cost
<strong>Alien Departure Point</strong>.</p>

<p>My opponent to the left, Red, started off with <strong>Rebel Cantina</strong>, but didn’t
really do anything with it, switching gears to more of an Alien scoring
strategy that featured <strong>Alien Cornucopia</strong>. Green, on the right, initially
began with the militaristic <strong>New Sparta</strong>, but like his counterpart, never
fully took advantage of it.</p>

<p>The final scores were 82-61-49, with me winning the day and Red bringing
up the rear. 82 is about as high as I can remember ever scoring, but
it’s certainly not high compared to scores I’ve seen posted by others.</p>

<h3>Game 2: Brown World Rush</h3>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/JwkQ/brown_world_rush.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/Jy5m/brown_world_rush_sm.jpg" title="Brown World Rush" alt="Screenshot - Brown World Rush" /></a></p>

<p>The second game was very different from the first. I took full advantage
of the special ability of my start world, <strong>Galactic Scavengers</strong>, which
allowed me to stash one card from every purchase I made, and recover
them on every produce phase. This can be very powerful when used
properly. It basically equates to a 1-card “manufacturer’s rebate” on
everything you buy.</p>

<p>My starting hand also contained both <strong>Alpha Centauri</strong> and <strong>Gem Smugglers</strong>,
two brown worlds that gave discounts on brown worlds, so it was pretty
clear what direction I had to take. An early <strong>Improved Logistics</strong> helped
me rush to fill out my tableau with a bunch of other brown and blue
worlds before either of the other players got their engines fully
started. I didn’t even bother playing a 6-cost dev because it would have
slowed me down too much. I did have to prestige-consume in the final
turn, however, because Green was coming on strong.</p>

<p>Final scores were 33-30-18, again in my favor. Red had a terrible
showing, but he actually took over one of my military worlds at the end,
almost as if he were trying to play kingmaker. Green nearly stole the
game with <strong>Terraforming Guild</strong> and his 3 windfall worlds.</p>

<h3>Game 3: Mining League</h3>

<p><a href="http://2dr.se/Jwuy/mining_league.jpg"><img src="http://2dr.se/JxZc/mining_league_sm.jpg" title="Mining League" alt="image" /></a></p>

<p>Initially, I went after a Rebel strategy, but when the cards weren’t
there, I committed to the <strong>Mining League</strong>. I was able to get 3 quality
brown production worlds and <strong>Mining Robots</strong> played, but Red put together a
very nice consume-based strategy from the very start, and eventually
blew by me with a pile of victory point chips before I got close to
hitting 12 cards in my tableau. I think Green might have helped Red out
a little too much, because he kept producing in order to get prestige.
Oh well.</p>

<p>This score was 53-44-25, with Red winning, me in second, and Green last.
The game ended due to VP chips running out, with Red claiming 33 of
them. I shake my fist at you, Red.</p>

<h3>Check out Keldon’s AI for RFTG</h3>

<p>Whether your computing platform of choice is PC, Mac, or Linux, if you
want to learn <em>Race for the Galaxy</em> or improve your gameplay, look no
further than Keldon’s excellent AI. It’s superb, it’s cross-platform,
it’s a <a href="http://www.keldon.net/rftg/">free download</a>, and the
<a href="http://riograndegames.com/uploads/Game/Game_240_gameRules.pdf">rules</a>
of <em>Race for the Galaxy</em>
(<a href="http://riograndegames.com/uploads/Game/Game_253_gameRules.pdf">and</a>
<a href="http://riograndegames.com/uploads/Game/Game_301_gameRules.pdf">its</a>
<a href="http://riograndegames.com/uploads/Game/Game_357_gameRules.pdf">expansions</a>)
are freely available from Rio Grande Games.</p>

<p>For the legally astute, Rio Grande Games, the publisher of <em>Race for the
Galaxy</em>, has given Keldon permission to use actual card images and names in the
app, so it’s all above board. Play away.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lord of the Rings: The Confrontation]]></title>
    <link href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/lotr-the-confrontation/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-05T10:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cubepusher.com/blog/lotr-the-confrontation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Never underestimate Dr. Knizia. His games usually seems laughably simple on
paper, but often have a sly mechanic or clever end-game scoring that make them
enjoyable brain-burners. Consider
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/9674/ingenious">Ingenious</a>, which would be
a ordinary abstract game in the hands of a lesser designer. However, the
scoring in that game is based on your lowest color peg instead of the highest
(or cumulative) score. That one twist turns the game on its head where you
constantly fine-tune your moves to advance your pegs.</p>

<p>That brings me to the under-appreciated
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/18833/lord-of-the-rings-the-confrontation-deluxe-edition">Lord of the Rings: The Confrontation</a>
(2002). I think this is a real gem of a 2-player game that may be overlooked by
players seeking meatier “War of the Ring” games who might dismiss this merely
as <a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/1917/stratego">Stratego</a> with a pasted
Tolkien theme. But there’s more than meets the eye here.</p>

<h2>Gameplay</h2>

<p>The mechanics are so simple that young players and gateway gamers will be able
to pick it up easily. Each player chooses either the Fellowship side or the
Sauron side of a board depicting Middle Earth. The Fellowship has 9 game pieces
on a small board, and need to get one piece (Frodo) to Mordor, which is on the
opposite side. Sauron has 9 different pieces, and needs to defeat Frodo or get
three enemies to the Shire, which is on his opposite side. Each character piece
has a different ability, and is assigned a strength number from 0 to 9.</p>

<p>The actual identity of the pieces are hidden from the other player (that’s the
Stratego element), so neither player knows if they are attacking a powerful
minion or a small whelp of a character. Moreover, multiple characters can
occupy non-mountain places on the board and swap pieces. So a clever player can
constantly play a shell-game of hiding their valuable pieces so their enemy
never knows which is which. It makes this into a great bluffing games, instead
of the open battleground of <em>Chess</em>, where every piece is known and every piece’s
ability can be spotted at a glance.</p>

<p>Players also have a set of nine battle cards that range from attack modifiers
(e.g., adding +2 to your strength) to special abilities (e.g., retreat
backwards). Each player gets one movement, then (if a battle results) they
resolve the battle with the character ability. If that doesn’t solve the
battle, then the numbered strength is used and added to the simultaneously
revealed battle cards. The battle is resolved and it is the next player’s turn.
It’s not a difficult game at first glance.</p>

<h2>Why it is So Good</h2>

<p>Not many 20-30 minute games have this much tension, are this easy to learn, yet
have an enjoyable theme. On the surface, it is <em>Stratego</em> with a LOTR theme. But
then there are these wonderful Knizia innovations. For one, the board is
diamond shaped, so the movement spreads outward from your starting position,
then funnels inward to the tight enemy territory. Secondly, there are the
mountains in the center where your abilities are hampered.</p>

<p>This would not be much of a challenge in <em>Chess</em>, but in this game characters
must always move forward (with few exceptions). They are mostly pawn-like and
cannot move backwards or sideways. So the diamond-shaped board requires that
you think several moves ahead before moving. You can “dodge” other pieces by
moving to the extreme right or left in this respect because of the ingenious
shape of the board.</p>

<p>The abilities also fit the characters nicely. So the Witch King can attack
sideways, since he is a flying character, while all the other characters can
only attack from the front. Borimir can act like a “bomb” and auto-eliminate
both the attacker and himself. There’s lots of richness in these abilities that
fits the theme and storytelling.</p>

<h2>Deeper than it Seems</h2>

<p>I thought the game would be too easy. But like many of Knizia’s games, the end
game is brain-burning fun. Like Battle Line, by the end of the game you are
forced to make a game-changing decision from only 1-3 possible moves. Having
the mechanic where most characters can only move forward means that you weigh
each decision carefully and decide in advance which characters you can afford
to sacrifice and which must be held by the end game. However, you also need
scout characters to probe the enemy. One misstep and you’ve given your enemy
the ability to win with no possible defense.</p>

<p>The good and evil sides are also balanced in unexpected ways. Sauron’s forces
are much stronger, but the Fellowship’s forces have many retreat capabilities
and are often very slippery. In addition, the board benefits the Fellowship by
giving them a sideways move and a shortcut through the mountains that Sauron’s
forces cannot use.</p>

<p>The hidden nature of the characters also means that the character’s identity is
often not known by the attacker until after they attack. So that (plus the
battle cards) adds a nice bluffing/tactical element to the game that adds much
more tactical fun to the game.</p>

<h2>Concluding Thoughts</h2>

<p>I happily add <em>Lord of the Rings: The Confrontation</em> to the short list of great
2-player quick games (a short list including
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/2655/hive">Hive</a>,
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/760/battle-line">Battle Line</a>, and
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/28143/race-for-the-galaxy">Race for the Galaxy</a>).
Like those other games, it’s a tough act to follow — the game has to be quick,
it has to be tactical, yet it can’t be as paralyzing as a tough game of Chess.</p>

<p>The Tolkien theme works beautifully and is probably the most thematic of
Knizia’s games. You feel the desperation of Frodo when playing the Fellowship
and using the mountains, retreats, and subtle bluffing to slip into Mordor
while you feel the vice-like grip of Sauron with his pieces. The Sauron side
likewise feels powerful but a bit clueless as to which character is Frodo and
how to prevent him from landing in Mordor. Sauron uses his higher-strength
characters to remove as many pieces on the board, while the Fellowship has
a nice variety of evasive tactics that make them escape Sauron’s net easily.</p>

<p>Knizia may be accused of pasted themes and regurgitating old games. But
I challenge any designer to come up with a more enjoyable, streamlined,
inexpensive, 2-player, 30-minute game than <em>Lord of the Rings: The
Confrontation</em>. It’s just one of those quick and precise games where you
wouldn’t want to change a single rule in fear that the elegant rules would
collapse.</p>

<p>&mdash;John Soety</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brass]]></title>
    <link href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/brass/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-27T10:24:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cubepusher.com/blog/brass</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/28720/brass">Brass</a> is a medium-weight
strategy board game for 3 to 4 players. It was designed by Martin Wallace, and
was first published in 2007 by <a href="http://www.warfroggames.com/">Warfrog Games</a> in
the UK. Since then, it has been distributed in US, and to date, has enjoyed two
successful reprints. The copy of the game used in this review is the first US
edition.</p>

<p>Please note: This is just a general overview and review of the game, not
a careful walk-through of the rules. There is plenty of in-depth
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/forums/thing/28720/brass">discussion of Brass</a>
in the forums at
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com">BoardGameGeek</a>, if that’s what you’re after.</p>

<h2>A brief rundown</h2>

<p>In the game of <em>Brass</em>, you are an industrialist entrepreneur in 19th-century
Lancashire, England. Your goal is to build cotton mills, coal mines, iron
works, ports, shipyards, canals, and railways, each of which can be used by you
(and the other players) in some fashion to earn money and score points.
Meanwhile, the other players are trying to do the same thing – it’s a race to
see who can best take advantage of the economy.</p>

<p><em>Brass</em> is one of those games that encourages you to plan out your actions ahead
of time. In order to score, you have to build. In order to build, for example,
not only must you have enough pounds to pay for the building, but you often
must have coal as well, and you’ll be presented the choice of developing your
own coal mines, using someone else’s mines (which gives them victory points),
or buying coal at the market price.</p>

<p>One extremely cool aspect of the economy in <em>Brass</em> is that players influence
both demand <em>and</em> supply. If there is a glut of coal on the board, then it can
be had very cheaply. In a coal shortage, you’ll pay dearly for it (as well as
raise the price for players who buy after you). Of course, you can always build
a coal mine to increase the supply, thereby driving the price down and earning
you income at the same time.</p>

<p>That was just one example. There is far more to <em>Brass</em> than I’m describing here,
but suffice it to say that it’s a deep, tense, satisfying experience to play.
More on that later.</p>

<h2>What’s in the box?</h2>

<p>The physical components of <em>Brass</em> are amazingly good, with one exception which
I’ll mention now: the coins. The coins are categorically awful, nothing more
than plastic tiddly-winks that are difficult to stack, and have a propensity
for slipping (and even flying) all over the place. Throw them away, and use
poker chips instead.</p>

<p>Now that the one truly negative bit has been outed, I’ll focus on the
overwhelmingly positive. First, the artwork is absolutely fantastic, very
thematic and evocative of the period. The game board presents the rough
geographical location of each town featured in the game, as well as several
flavor illustrations. The cards are attractive and quite useable.</p>

<p>The player colors (red, yellow, green, purple) are well chosen, and easily
distinguishable. Each player receives his/her own set of hefty and well-printed
building tiles in his/her color. The wooden bits are quite adequate, as one
might expect of any serious Eurogame: black and orange cubes to represent coal
and iron, respectively.</p>

<p>Lastly, I must admit that the rulebook, although well-set typographically and
attractive graphically, is horribly organized. The rules aren’t simple as it
is, and the way the rules are organized certainly doesn’t make them any easier.
Thankfully, there are resources available on BoardGameGeek to help clarify the
rulebook’s shortcomings.</p>

<h2>How to play (in a nutshell)</h2>

<p>Player order is not seating order, as it is with most games. In <em>Brass</em>, the
money players spend is tracked, and the player that spent the least in the
previous round is first player in the next round, second-lowest spender = 2nd
player, and so on. Thus, the player order will most likely change from round to
round. This is a really cool balancing mechanism that I wish more games had.
You have to watch your spending, because this will affect your order in the
next round, and therefore your choices of which spaces are left available on
the board (the early players get first choice of the prime locations).</p>

<p>Another trick is that only the top tile on each of your personal industry
stacks is available to be built. Typically (but not always), the more rewarding
tiles are towards the bottom of each stack, so each player has to choose
whether to build down through a particular industry, or develop the industry
(remove tiles off the top).</p>

<p>The game takes place over two Eras: the Canal Era and the Rail Era,
respectively. You start with a hand of 8 cards, each of which contains either
a location on the board (for example, the city of Manchester) or a type of
industry (cotton, coal, iron, port, or shipyard). Each turn, you will take
2 actions, discard a card for each action. At the end of your turn, you draw
back up to 8 cards. An Era ends when all players run out of cards (not when the
deck is depleted).</p>

<p>As what to do for an action, you may do any of the following five things:</p>

<ul>
<li>Take a loan (cash infusion)</li>
<li>Build a link between cities (canal or rail)</li>
<li>Build an industry in a city (cotton/coal/iron/port/shipyard)</li>
<li>Develop an industry (remove 1-2 tiles from the top of your stack(s))</li>
<li>Sell cotton (increase per-round income)</li>
</ul>


<p>Here’s the rub: For an industry tile you’ve played to be any good, it needs to
be used, or <em>flipped</em>. Cotton mills and ports can be flipped when a player
sells cotton. Coal mine and iron works tiles are built with a certain amount of
coal or iron sitting on them, and get flipped when their respective resources
are depleted. When a tile is flipped, it is literally turned upside down to
reveal the per-round income it will earn you, and how many points it’s worth at
scoring. You won’t get any income or points for your unflipped (unused)
industries, so only build what you think has a chance be used before the end of
an Era.</p>

<p>A good rule of thumb is to try to build more of what other players are building
less of. The demand will come, and the fewer players you have to share that
demand with, all the better for you!</p>

<h2>Scoring points</h2>

<p>At the end of each Era, there is a round of scoring. Players get points for
their flipped industry tiles and for their links to industrialized cities.
After scoring the Canal (first) Era, all canal links and level 1 industry tiles
are removed from the board, leaving a partially clean board for the beginning
of the Rail Era.</p>

<h2>Elsewhere</h2>

<p>In the interest of (relative) brevity, I won’t get into any more specifics
about the rules here, but Warfrog has a downloadable PDF of the
<a href="http://www.warfroggames.com/images/rules_eng.pdf">rules</a>, as well as a <a href="http://www.warfroggames.com/brassfaq.html">FAQ
page</a> for those that are interested
in learning more about how the game works. You’ll also want to check out the
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/file/download/2ld7ry1ift/Brass_Restructured_Rules_v1.pdf">rewritten
rules</a>
on BoardGameGeek after seeing the official ones! The BGG
<a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/forum/0/thing/28720">forums</a> for <em>Brass</em> are another
great resource if you have rules questions, or just want to read what other
people have to say about the game. Finally, BGG has a wonderful <a href="http://boardgamegeek.com/images/thing/28720">image
gallery</a> of people playing <em>Brass</em>,
some of the playing pieces, etc. All of the images used in this review are
courtesy of BGG users.</p>

<h2>The Review</h2>

<p><em>Brass</em> is an absolutely brilliant game, and I’m thrilled to have the chance to
share my thoughts on it. It’s certainly not a simple game, and you’ll probably
play it wrong on your first attempt (as I did), but I’ve found it to be a true
gem after several plays, and I don’t expect my opinion to change anytime soon.
<em>Brass</em> shares much in common with old-school railroad games, but emerges as its
own unique experience.</p>

<p>Playing <em>Brass</em> actually makes me feel a bit like a 19th-century English
businessman. Wallace has clearly designed the game to be thematic. Yes, there
are some niggly rules exceptions, but the mechanics of <em>Brass</em> are largely
refined abstractions of business processes from the period. Taking into account
the geographical element, it’s amazing how much complexity Wallace was able to
distill into a really fun, and relatively simple game. The game’s soul draws me
in.</p>

<p><em>Brass</em> can be quite contentious and cutthroat with 4 players, and slightly less
so with 3. With either number, there will always be that delicious tension
between wanting to increase your income, score more points, and position
yourself to grab the prime locations on the board, whilst trying not to run out
of money or have your plans foiled by the other players, all of whom are trying
to do the same thing. There is a lot going on, and there will always be more
you want to do than you are able to do – a sign of a solid and worthy game.
I highly recommend <em>Brass</em> to those who like their games meaty and strategic, and
who don’t mind using their first play or two of <em>Brass</em> to learn how to play it.</p>

<p>&mdash;Stephen Tudor</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ra]]></title>
    <link href="http://cubepusher.com/blog/ra/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-26T10:41:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://cubepusher.com/blog/ra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For my first review of a board game, I’d like to feature a true classic:
<a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/game/12">Ra</a>, by prolific game designer Reiner
Knizia. Knizia has designed hundreds of board and card games, but among gamers,
Ra is widely considered to be one of his finest creations.</p>

<p>Ra is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurogame">Eurogame</a> with a pasted-on
Egyptian theme. What I mean by this is that, in the end, it’s really an auction
game that could just as easily have been about space ships, dinosaurs, or fine
art. It could have been about anything else, and it would play exactly the same
way. The gameplay has little to do with Egypt, and the theme has little to do
with what makes Ra a great game. The credit for that goes to the game’s core
mechanics, and that is what places Ra squarely in the Eurogame camp: Its main
focus is on the gameplay itself, rather than the theme.</p>

<p>I’m reviewing the Überplay edition of Ra, which I own. I understand that
Überplay is now defunct, but Rio Grande Games has picked up the rights to
publish the next edition Ra, and that printing will probably hit shelves in
2009.</p>

<h2>What’s in the box?</h2>

<p>In addition to the nicely printed (and short) rules booklet, there is a board,
a canvas bag, “sun” auction markers, scoring counters, a Ra figurine, and
a bunch of cardboard tiles (and by a bunch of tiles, I mean a whole lot of
tiles).</p>

<p>The board is little more than a pair of “tracks” for auction tiles to sit on.
Fortunately, it’s not entirely pointless, as it also contains a simple
reference that reminds how the different types of tiles are scored. I suppose
the only other justification for the board is its Egyptian-themed artwork,
which can help reinforce an otherwise weak theme. As I’ve already pointed out,
though, the theme is of no real importance to this game.</p>

<p>When you score points in Ra, you receive little “tablets” with quasi-Egyptian
numerals on them. They come in denominations of 1, 2, 5, and 10. A cool way to
keep track of how many points you have throughout the game.</p>

<p>The auction markers are wooden “sun” pieces, numbered 1-16. In an auction,
players bid with these suns, and ties don’t happen because there are no
duplicate numbers. The heart of the game, however, is the enormous complement
of auction tiles, and there are quite a few of them. The different types of
auction tiles you’ll come across are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pharaoh</li>
<li>Nile</li>
<li>Flood</li>
<li>Civilization</li>
<li>Monument</li>
<li>Disaster</li>
<li>God</li>
<li>Gold</li>
<li>Epoch</li>
</ul>


<h2>How to play (in a nutshell)</h2>

<p><em>Ra</em> is all about <strong>auctions</strong>. Every auction gives players a chance to win a set
of tiles. The basic gist is that you can choose to do one of three possible
things on your turn:</p>

<ol>
<li>Draw a tile from the bag and place it on the board.</li>
<li>Call for an auction to begin.</li>
<li>Discard one of your god tiles and claim a single tile of your choice
on the board.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Scoring points</h2>

<p><em>Ra</em> is played in three rounds, or Epochs. An Epoch comes to an end when the <em>Ra</em>
tile track fills up, or when everyone has played all their suns. At the end of
each Epoch, players score points for the tiles they own. The goal is to have
the most points at the end of the game.</p>

<h2>Elsewhere…</h2>

<p>In the interest of (relative) brevity, I won’t get into the details of the
rules any further here, but BoardGameGeek has a downloadable PDF of the
<a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/file/download/6057/RA.pdf">rules</a> for those that
are interested in learning more about how the game works. The BGG
<a href="http://www.boardgamegeek.com/forum/0/boardgame/12">forums</a> for <em>Ra</em> are also
a great resource to check out if you have rules questions, or just want to read
what other people have to say about the game. BGG also has a wonderful image
gallery of people playing <em>Ra</em>, some of the playing pieces, etc.</p>

<h2>The Review</h2>

<p><em>Ra</em> is such a simple, smart, easy-to-teach game. It’s just plain fun, and I’d
recommend it to almost anybody, even many non-gamers. It plays pretty quickly,
and the press-your-luck element is fantastic. Everyone I’ve introduced to <em>Ra</em>
has loved it, too. Despite the loose-fitting theme, the game is still visually
rich. Yelling “RA!” when you want to start an auction is a blast as well.
I very highly recommend <em>Ra</em>.</p>

<p>I would say that the biggest hurdle for newcomers to <em>Ra</em> would be picking up on
how some of the scoring works, but even that isn’t too cumbersome. There’s
a cheat sheet on the game board that summarizes the scoring very nicely, and
it’s not too hard to get used to. Like most games, the best way to learn how to
play it is to play it.</p>

<p>The bidding is streamlined, and the other players’ suns are easy to read across
the table, so you will always have an idea of how likely you are to win those
tiles you want. There are often plenty of opportunities to bluff or force
someone else to play their high sun too early, setting you up to win a bigger
auction later. That is, if the Epoch doesn’t end first!</p>

<p>There is wonderful tension in <em>Ra</em>. Players are constantly balancing the desire
to wait and get the best value for their suns with the knowledge that they need
to get what tiles they can before the end of the round arrives. The game is
a ticking clock, and everyone feels it.</p>

<p>In conclusion, <em>Ra</em> is one of my favorite games. It’s not a terribly heavy or
complex strategy game, and there is a bit of luck/chaos due to the draw bag,
but it still rewards smart play most of the time. Most importantly, it’s
ridiculously fun, and doesn’t take all night to play. In the end, those two
things are what makes it so much more likely to hit the table than some other
really good games. Even if the Egyptian thing was just tacked on at the last
minute.</p>

<p>&mdash;Stephen Tudor</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
